Diaries Collection 1984.0029
Archives and Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Library
Diaries Collection
1851-1943
Archives and Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Library
1984.0029
2.5 Linear Feet
Diaries dating from the 19th century provide information on mid-century farm life, social activities, local travel and education at a one room school. Two "thoughts diaries" of the same period give one man's views on Christianity, human nature and slavery. Travel journals from the later part of the century describe trips through European countries; these also contain information on transportation and lodging. Those dating from the 20th century reveal much about the life of a Connecticut female artist and her thoughts and feelings concerning World War II. Also included is the 1943 diary of a University of Connecticut coed and the 1902 diary of a Hartford store employee.
Access
The collection is open and available for research.
Acquisition Information
Additional diaries are added as they are acquired.
History
Diaries dating from the 19th century provide information on mid-century farm life, social activities, local travel and education at a one room school. Two "thoughts diaries" of the same period give one man's views on Christianity, human nature and slavery. Travel journals from the later part of the century describe trips through European countries; these also contain information on transportation and lodging.
Those dating from the 20th century reveal much about the life of a Connecticut female artist and her thoughts and feelings concerning World War II. Also included is the 1943 diary of a University of Connecticut coed (Ann T. Winchester) and the 1902 diary of a Hartford store employee (Phineas Gofriels).
Custodial History
The collection was transferred to Historical Manuscripts and Archives in 1984 from the Special Collections Department, Homer Babbidge Library. The Stanton diaries were added in April 1989. In 1995, Special Collections and Historical Manuscripts and Archives merged to form Archives &and Special Collections now located in the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center. Additional diaries are added as they are acquired.
Scope and Content
The personal diaries of thirteen known individuals, two anonymous diaries, and four travel journals. Individual descriptions of the contents are listed with the collection listing.
College students; Farms; General stores; Voyages and travels; Art; Connecticut (state); Diaries; Nineteenth century; Agriculture; Universities and colleges; Education; Storrs (inhabited place); University of Connecticut
- Series I: Diaries, 1792-1943
  - Field, Harriet Kingsbury, 1853-1857 (Box 2)
  - Geer, Elihu, 1857 January - November (Box 5)
  - Gabriel, George Henry, 1902 (Box 1)
    Biography
    2 November 1864 - 19 November 1954.
  - Ransom, George, 1844-1847 (Volume D2592)
    Scope and Content Note
    Journal kept by Sherwood B. Ransom, of East Haddam, Connecticut, during a whaling voyage 1844-1848. Ransom was a boatsteerer (harpooneer) on the whaling ship Morrison, sailing out of New London, CT. Journal contains information on the day-to-day life and business of whaling as well as Ransom's personal reflections, but only records the period 1844-1845, as well as some entries from 1847. A letter from his father, George Ransom, and a lock of hair are tucked into the back of the journal volume. Two other journals and record-books exist from this voyage of the Morrison, both of which are held by Mystic Seaport and have been digitalized. The first, the account book of Samuel Green, Jr., the captain of the vessel, can be found here: http://library.mysticseaport.org/initiative/PageImage.cfm?BibID=33154. The second, the journal of the Reverend Thomas Douglass, can be found here: http://library.mysticseaport.org/initiative/PageImage.cfm?BibID=31902.
  - Robbins, Laroy T., 1877-1884 (Box 2)
  - Smith, Edwin, 1856-1865 (Box 2)
  - Stanton, Daniel, 1863 (Box 2)
  - Stanton, G. V., 1889 (Box 2)
  - Warren, Edward S., 1849-1862 (Box 4)
    Samuel Edward Warren (SEW), born October 29, 1831, in Weston Newton, MA, the son of Samuel and Catherine (Reed) Warren. He attended the Teacher's Seminary at Phillips Academy in Andover, MA. After leaving the Academy, Warren attended Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute as a student and received a degree as a civil engineer (class of 1851) before becoming a descriptive geometry and drawing teacher. He then moved on to the Massachusetts Institute of Technology and Massachusetts Normal Art School. His last employment was as a private instructor and author of books on geometry.
    Warren died in Newton, MA in July 1909. Additional volumes of his diary have been located at the University of Delaware and the Winterthur Library.
  - Whitlock, 1924-1943 (Box 3)
  - Winchester, Ann T., 1943 (Box 2)
- Series II: Copybooks
  - Oehlshlager, J. C., undated (Box 1)
  - Unidentified, undated (Box 5)
- Series III: Travel Journals
  - Green, Ezra M., 1873 (Box 1)
  - Fairbanks, F. A., 1865 (Box 1)
  - Rillaney, 1867 (Box 1)
  - Walker, Dean and Thayer, Addison P., 1851-? (Box 2)
  - Unidentified, 1882-1883 (Box 5)
  - Unidentified, 1872-1873 (Box 5)
  - Unidentified, 1890 June - August (Box 5)
  - Unidentified, 1891-1892 (Box 5)
- Series III: Signature albums (autograph album)
  - Clark, Mary, 1835-1838 (Box 1)